Most of you can probably relate to what I'm feeling right now.
على الأرجح أن معظمكم يشعر بما أشعر به الآن
My heart is racing in my chest.
دقاتٌ قلبي تتسارع.
My palms are a little bit clammy.
راحتا يديّ باردتان قليلاً.
I'm sweating.
أنا أتعرّق.
And my breath is a little bit shallow.
ونفسى يتقطّع قليلاً.
Now, these familiar sensations are obviously the result
الآن هذه الأحاسيس المألوفة من الواضح أنها نتيجة
of standing up in front of a thousand of you
الوقوف أمام ألف منكم
and giving a talk that might be streamed online
وإلقاء كلمة ربما تُبث على الإنترنت
to perhaps a million more.
من المحتمل لمليون آخرين.
But the physical sensations I'm experiencing right now
لكن الأحاسيس الجسدية التى أشهدها الآن
My nervous system is sending a flood of hormones
يرسل جهازى العصبى تيارً من الهرمونات
like cortisol and adrenaline into my bloodstream.
كالكُورْتِيزول والأَدرينالين فى مجرى الدم.
It's a very old and very necessary response that sends blood and oxygen
إنها استجابة مألوفة وضرورية جداً حيث يرسل الدم والأوكسجبن
to the organs and muscles that I might need
إلى الأعضاء والعضلات التي ربما أحتاجها
to respond quickly to a potential threat.
في استجابةٍ سريعة لتهديد محتمل.
But there's a problem with this response,
لكن يوجد مشكلة فى هذه الاستجابة،
and that is, it can get over-activated.
وهى أنه قد تتجاوز الحد المطلوب.
particularly over an extended period of time,
خصوصاً على مدى فترةٍ طويلة
So basically, if this response happens infrequently: super-necessary
على هذا الأساس، لو حدثت هذه الاستجابة على نحو متقطع فهي ضرورة مُلحة
for my well-being and survival.
لسعادتى وبقائي.
But if it happens too much,
لكن إن تكررت كثيراً
it can actually make me sick.
فمن الممكن أن تسّبب لي المرض.
between chronic stress and illness.
بين الضغط المزمن والمرض.
Things like heart disease and even cancer
فأشياء مثل مرض القلب وحتى السرطان
are being shown to have a relationship to stress.
أظهرت صلة لها بالضغط.
And that's because, over time, too much activation from stress
ولأنه بمرور الوقت النشاط المتزايد من الضغط
can interfere with my body's processes that keep me healthy.
يمكن أن يتداخل مع سيرعمل جسمي الشيء الذي يحافظ على صحتى.
Now, let's imagine for a moment that I was pregnant.
دعونا نتخيل للحظة أننى كنت حاملاً
What might this kind of stress,
بالنظر إلى هذا النوع من الضغط
particularly over the length of my pregnancy,
خصوصاً طوال فترة حملي
what kind of impact might that have
ما نوع التأثير الذى ربما يتركه ذلك
on the health of my developing fetus?
على صحة نمو جنيني؟
You probably won't be surprised when I tell you
قد لا تعتريكم الدهشة إذا ما أخبرتكم
that this kind of stress during pregnancy is not good.
أن هذا النوع من الضغط أثناء الحمل شيء سيء.
It can even cause the body to initiate labor too early,
فقد يدفع ذلك الجسد إلى ولادة مبكرة جداً،
because in a basic sense, the stress communicates
بحسب طبيعة الأشياء، فإن الضغط يوحي
that the womb is no longer a safe place for the child.
بأن الرحم لم يعد مكانً آمناً للطفل.
Stress during pregnancy is linked with things like high blood pressure
الضغط أثناء الحمل متصل بأشياءٍ كضغط الدم المرتفع
and low infant birth weight,
ووزن المولود المنخفض،
and it can begin a cascade of health challenges
ويمكن أن يتسبّب ذلك في تغيراتٍ صحيةٍ متتالية
that make birth much more dangerous
تجعل أمر الولادة أكثر خطورة
for both parent and child.
لكل من الأُم والطفل.
Now of course stress, particularly in our modern lifestyle,
الآن بالطبع يُعدّ الضغط خصوصاً مع أسلوب حياتنا المعاصر،
is a somewhat universal experience, right?
تجربةً عالمية بعض الشئ، أليس كذلك؟
Maybe you've never stood up to give a TED Talk,
ربما لم تقف لتلقي خطاباً فى مؤتمر تيد،
but you've faced a big presentation at work,
لكنك كنت ملزماً بعرضٍ تقديميٍ كبير فى العمل
a sudden job loss,
أو فقدان عمل مفاجيء،
a big test,
أو اختبارٍ مهم،
a heated conflict with a family member or friend.
أو خلاف محتدم مع أحد أفراد الأسرة أو صديق.
and whether we're able to stay in a relaxed state long enough
وسواء استطعنا البقاء فى حالة استرخاء وقتاً كافياً
depends a lot on who we are.
يعتمد ذلك كثيراً على من نكون.
There's also a growing body of research
أيضاً يوجد بحث له صدى كبير
showing that people who experience more discrimination
يُظهر أن الناس الذين يعانون كثيراً من التفرقة
are more likely to have poor health.
أكثر عرضة للدخول فى حالة صحية سيئة.
Even the threat of discrimination,
حتى التهديد بالتفرقة،
like worrying you might be stopped by police while driving your car,
كقلقك من احتمال أن توقفك الشرطة أثناء قيادتك السيارة،
Harvard Professor Dr. David Williams,
دكتور (ديفيد ويليام) الأستاذ فى جامعة هارفارد
the person who pioneered the tools that have proven these linkages,
هو الشخص الذى ابتكر الأدوات التى أثبتت هذه الروابط،
says that the more marginalized groups in our society
يقول أن المجموعات الأكثر عرضة للتهميش فى مجتمعنا
experience more discrimination and more impacts on their health.
يعانون أكثر من التفرقة ويعانون من تأثيرات كثيرة على صحتهم.
I've been interested in these issues for over a decade.
لقد كنت مهتمة بهذه القضية لأكثر من عقد من الزمان.
I became interested in maternal health
أصبحت مهتمة بصحة الأمهات
when a failed premed trajectory instead sent me down a path
عندما فشلت فى مسارى للطب وبدلاً من ذلك أودت بى إلى طريق
looking for other ways to help pregnant people.
أبحث فيه عن طرق أخرى لمساعدة الحوامل.
I became a doula,
فأصبحت قابلة،
a lay person trained to provide support
تدرّب الشخص العادي لتقديم الدعم
to people during pregnancy and childbirth.
للناس أثناء الحمل والولادة.
And because I'm Latina and a Spanish speaker,
ولأننى لاتينية وأتحدث الإسبانية
in my first volunteer doula gig at a public hospital in North Carolina,
ففى أول مشاركة تطوعية لى كقابلة في مستشفى عام فى كارولاينا الشمالية
I saw clearly how race and class impacted the experiences
رأيت بوضوح كيف يؤثر العِرق والطبقة على معاناة
of the women that I supported.
النساء اللواتي أساعدهن.
If we take a look at the statistics about the rates of illness
لو ألقينا نظرة على الإحصائيات عن معدلات المرض
during pregnancy and childbirth,
أثناء الحمل والولادة،
we see clearly the pattern outlined by Dr. Williams.
نرى بوضوح النموذج الذى وضعه د (ويليام).
African-American women in particular
وخصوصاً النساء الأمريكيات من أصل إفريقي
have an entirely different experience than white women
يتعرضن لتجربةٍ مختلفةٍ تماماً عن النساء البيض
when it comes to whether their babies are born healthy.
حينما يتعلق الأمر بصحة أطفالهم الجيّدة حين الولادة.
In certain parts of the country, particularly the Deep South,
فى مناطق معينة فى الدولة تحديداً فى عمق الجنوب،
the rates of mother and infant death for black women
معدلات موت الأم والطفل للنساء السود
actually approximate those rates in Sub-Saharan African.
فى الحقيقة تقارب معدلات الدول الإفريقية جنوب الصحراء الكبرى.
In those same communities,
فى نفس هذه المجتمعات،
the rates for white women are near zero.
معدلات النساء البيض تقترب من الصفر.
Even nationally, black women are four times more likely
على الصعيد الوطني، النساء السود أكثر عرضةً بأربع مرات
to die during pregnancy and childbirth
للموت أثناء الحمل والولادة
than white women.
من النساء البيض.
Four times more likely to die.
أكثر عرضةً للموت بأربع مرات.
They're also twice as likely for their infants to die
وهم أكثر عرضةً مرتين لموت أطفالهم
before the first year of life
قبل السنة الأولى من حياتهم
than white infants,
من الأطفال البيض،
and two to three times more likely
وأكثر عرضةً مرتين أو ثلاثة
to give birth too early or too skinny --
للولادة مبكراً أو قد يكون جسمه هزيلاً --
a sign of insufficient development.
في مؤشرٍ على عجز النمو.
Native women are also more likely to have higher rates of these problems
السكّان الأصليون من النساء أكثر عرضة ليكون لديهن معدلات عالية من هذه المشاكل
than white women,
مقارنةً بالنساء البيض،
as are some groups of Latinas.
كبعض المجموعات اللاتينية.
For the last decade as a doula turned journalist and blogger,
خلال عملي في العقد الماضى كقابلة تحولت إلى الصحافة والتدوين،
I've been trying to raise the alarm
ظللت أحاول دقّ ناقوس الخطر
about just how different the experiences of women of color,
عن اختلاف تجارب النساء غير البيض،
are when it comes to pregnancy and birth in the US.
عندما يتعلق الأمر بالحمل والولادة فى الولايات المتحدة.
But when I tell people about these appalling statistics,
لكن حينما أخبر الناس عن هذه الإحصائيات المروّعة،
I'm usually met with an assumption that it's about either poverty
تكون إجاباتهم بإفتراض أنها بسبب الفقر
or lack of access to care.
أو غياب العناية الصحية.
But it turns out, neither of these things tell the whole story.
لكن تبيّن أنّ القصة ليست كما تبدو.
Even middle-class black women still have much worse outcomes
حتى النساء السود من الطبقة الوسطى لا تزال حالتهن سيئةً جداً
than their middle-class white counterparts.
مقارنةً بنظرائهن البيض من الطبقة الوسطى.
The gap actually widens among this group.
لا تزال الهوة تتسع بين هذه المجموعات.
And while access to care is definitely still a problem,
وعلى الرغم من أن الحصول على العناية لا يزال بالتأكيد مشكلة،
even women of color who receive the recommended prenatal care
حتى النساء غير البيض اللواتى يحصلن على الرعاية الموصى بها قبل الولادة
still suffer from these high rates.
لا يزلن يعانين من هذه المعدلات المرتفعة.
And so we come back to the path
ولذلك عدنا إلى الطريق
from discrimination to stress to poor health,
من التفرقة إلى التوتر إلى الصحة السيئة.
and it begins to paint a picture that many people of color know to be true:
مما يرسم لوحةً يقرّ معظم غير البيض بصحتها:
racism is actually making us sick.
العنصرية تصيبنا بالمرض حقاً.
Still sound like a stretch?
هل لا يزال هذا مبالغاً فيه؟
Consider this: immigrants, particularly black and Latina immigrants,
تأملوا هذا: المهاجرون خاصةً السود واللاتينيون،
actually have better health when they first arrive in the United States.
يتمتعون فى الحقيقة بصحة جيّدة حين وصولهم لأول مرة إلى الولايات المتحدة
But the longer they stay in this country, the worse their health becomes.
وكلما طال بقاؤهم فى هذا البلد تتردى صحتهم إلى الأسوء.
People like me, born in the United States to Cuban immigrant parents,
أشخاص مثلي وُلدوا في الولايات المتحدة لأبوين مهاجرَيْنِ من كوبا،
are actually more likely to have worse health than my grandparents did.
أكثر عرضةً فى الحقيقة لأن تتردى صحتهم إلى الأسوء أكثرمن أجدادي.
It's what researchers call "the immigrant paradox,"
هذا ما تسميه الأبحاث " تناقضات المهاجرين،"
and it further illustrates
ويوضّح كذلك
that there's something in the US environment
أن هناك شئ فى بيئة الولايات المتحدة
But here's the thing:
لكن إليكم الأمر:
this problem, that racism is making people of color,
مشكلة العنصرية هذه والتي تصيب غير البيض،
I could spend all of my time with you talking about it,
يمكنني قضاء وقتي كلّه أحدثكم عن هذا الأمر،
but I won't, because I want to make sure to tell you about one solution.
لكنني لا أريد ذلك، لأن ما يهمني أن أحدثكم عن حلٍ واحد.
And the good news is, it's a solution that isn't particularly expensive,
والخبر الجيّد أنه ليس حلاً غالياً بالضرورة،
and doesn't require any fancy drug treatments
وهو لا يتطلب علاجات طبية باهظة
or new technologies.
أو تقنيةً جديدة.
The solution is called, "The JJ Way."
يسمى الحل "طريقة جى جى."
Meet Jennie Joseph.
(مت جيني جوزيف)
She's a midwife in the Orlando, Florida area
هى قابلة فى أورلاندو بمنطقة فلوريدا
who has been serving pregnant women for over a decade.
والتي ظلت تخدم النساء الحوامل لأكثر من عقد من الزمان.
In what she calls her easy-access clinics,
فى ما تسميه بعياداتها السهلة والميّسرة،
Jennie and her team provide prenatal care to over 600 women per year.
تقدم (جينى) وفريقها الرعاية ما قبل الولادة لأكثر من 600 إمرأة سنوياً.
Her clients, most of whom are black, Haitian and Latina,
معظم عملائها من النساء السود والهاييتيّين واللاتينيين،
deliver at the local hospital.
واللواتي يلدن في المستشفى المحلي.
But by providing accessible and respectful prenatal care,
لكن بتقديمها الرعاية المتاحة والمحترمة ما قبل الولادة،
Jennie has achieved something remarkable:
حقّقت (جينى) شيئاً لافتاً للنظر:
almost all of her clients give birth to healthy, full-term babies.
يَلد معظم عملائها أطفالاً سليمين وبصحةٍ جيدة.
Her method is deceptively simple.
طريقتها بسيطة على نحو مخادع.
Jennie says that all of her appointments start at the front desk.
تقول (جينى) أنّ كل استعدادتها تبدأ من مكتب الإستقبال.
Every member of her team, and every moment a women is at her clinic,
كل عضو من فريقها وكل دقيقة تمضيها المرأة فى عيادتها
is as supportive as possible.
تحظى بالدعم قدر الإمكان.
No one is turned away due to lack of funds.
لا أحد يُستبعد لقلّة المال.
The JJ Way is to make the finances work no matter what the hurdles.
تتلخص "طريقة جى جى" في توفير الدعم المالي بغض النظر عن الصعوبات.
No one is chastised for showing up late to their appointments.
لا أحد يُجازى لتأخره عن مواعيده.
No one is talked down to or belittled.
لأحد يُستخف به أو يُقلّل من شأنه.
Jennie's waiting room feels more like your aunt's living room than a clinic.
حجرة انتظار (جينى) أشبه بحجرة معيشة عمتك أكثر من كونها عيادة.
She calls this space "a classroom in disguise."
تسمى هذا المكان "الفصل المموّه."
With the plush chairs arranged in a circle,
بكراسيه الفخمة والمرتبة على شكل دائرة،
women wait for their appointments in one-on-one chats
تنتظر النساء مواعيدهن وهن يتبادلن أطراف الحديث وجها لوجه
with a staff educator,
بوجود موظفٍ مختص،
or in group prenatal classes.
أو مجموعة فصول أثناء الحمل.
When you finally are called back to your appointment,
حينما يتصلون بك مجدداً لأجل موعدك،
you are greeted by Alexis or Trina,
يستقبلك (ألكسيس) أو (ترينا)،
two of Jennie's medical assistants.
اثنان من المساعدين الطبيّين ل(جيني).
Both are young, African-American and moms themselves.
كلاهما فتاتان أمريكيتان من أصول إفريقية وأمهات كذلك.
Their approach is casual and friendly.
تعاملهن عاديّ ولطيف.
During one visit I observed,
خلال زيارة ما لاحظت،
Trina chatted with a young soon-to-be mom
أن (ترينا) تحدثت مع فتاة على وشك الولادة
while she took her blood pressure.
بينما كانت تقيس ضغط دمها.
This Latina mom was having trouble keeping food down due to nausea.
هذه الأم اللاتينية كانت تعاني من مشكلة إبقاء الطعام فى جسدها بسسب الغثيان.
As Trina deflated the blood pressure cuff,
وبينما كانت تفرغ جهاز ضغط الدم،
she said, "We'll see about changing your prescription, OK?
قالت: "سوف ننظر فى تغيير وصفتك الطبية، حسناً؟
We can't have you not eating."
لا يمكن أن نتركك دون أكل."
That "we" is actually a really crucial aspect of Jennie's model.
وبهذه الكلمة "نحن،" يظهر الجانب الأساسي الحقيقي لنموذج (جيني).
She sees her staff as part of a team that, alongside the woman and her family,
ترى موظفيها كجزء من فريق إلى جانب المرأة وأسرتها
has one goal:
يسعى لهدف واحد:
get mom to term with a healthy baby.
أن تلد الأم طفلها بصحةٍ تامة.
Jennie says that Trina and Alexis are actually the center of her care model,
تقول (جيني) أن (ترينا) و(ألكسيس) هما فى الحقيقة عصب نموذجها في الرعاية،
and that her role as a provider is just to support their work.
وأن دورها كمُعين أن تدعم عملهن.
Trina spends a lot of her day on her cell phone,
تقضي (ترينا) معظم يومها على هاتفها الخلوي،
texting with clients about all sorts of things.
تراسل العملاء عن العديد من الأشياء.
One woman texted to ask if a medication she was prescribed at the hospital
راسلتها إمراة تسأل إذا ما كان الدواء الذي وُصِفَ لها في المستشفى
was OK to take while pregnant.
جيد لتأخذه أثناء فترة الحمل.
The answer was no.
وكانت الإجابة لا.
Another woman texted with pictures of an infant born under Jennie's care.
راسلتها إمراة أخرى بصور لطفل وُلد تحت رعاية (جيني).
Lastly, when you finally are called back to see the provider,
أخيرا، عندما يتم الإتصال بك مجدداً لترى مقدّم الخدمة،
you've already taken your own weight in the waiting room,
تكونين قد وزنتي نفسك سلفاً فى حجرة الإنتظار،
and done your own pee test in the bathroom.
وأخذتي عينةً لبولك فى الحمام.
This is a big departure from the traditional medical model,
يعتبر هذا تغييراً كبيراً عن النموذج الطبي المعهود،
because it places responsibility and information
لأن يضع المسؤولية والمعلومات
back in the woman's hands.
في يد المرأة.
So rather than a medical setting where you might be chastised
لذلك بدلاً عن الوضع الطبي الذي قد تعاقبين فيه
for not keeping up with provider recommendations --
على عدم التزامك بتوصيات الطبيب --
the kind of settings often available to low-income women --
نوع الإعداد المتاح غالباً للنساء ذوات الدخل المنخفض --
Jennie's model is to be as supportive as possible.
يعتبر نموذج (جيني) داعماً على قدر الإمكان.
And that support provides a crucial buffer
ويخفف هذا الدعم بدرجة كبيرة
to the stress of racism and discrimination facing these women every day.
من ضغط العنصرية والتمييز الذى يواجه هؤلاء النساء كل يوم.
But here's the best thing about Jennie's model:
لكن هنا أفضل شئ عن نموذج (جيني):
it's been incredibly successful.
لقد نجح بطريقة لا توصف.
Remember those statistics I told you,
تذكرون تلك الإحصائيات التى أخبرتكم عنها،
that black women are more likely to give birth too early,
أن النساء السود أكثر عرضةً للولادة مبكراً جداً،
to give birth to low birth weight babies,
أو ولادة أطفالٍ بأوزان أقل،
to even die due to complications of pregnancy and childbirth?
أو حتى الموت نظراً لمضاعفات الحمل والولادة؟
Well, The JJ Way has almost entirely eliminated those problems,
حسناً، تخلصت "طريقة جى جى" بالكامل تقريباً من هذه المشاكل،
starting with what Jennie calls "skinny babies."
تبدأ بما تسميه (جيني) "الأطفال الهزيلون."
She's been able to get almost all her clients to term
لقد كانت قادرة على الوصول بمعظم عملائها إلى وضع
with healthy, chunky babies like this one.
أطفالٍ سليمين ومكتنزين مثل هذا.
Audience: Aw!
الجمهور: أوه!
Miriam Zoila Pérez: This is a baby girl
ميريام زويلا: هذه طفلة
born to a client of Jennie's this past June.
ولدت لعميلة عند (جيني) فى يونيو المنصرم.
A similar demographic of women in Jennie's area
التشابه السكّاني للنساء فى منطقة (جيني)
who gave birth at the same hospital her clients did
اللواتي ولدن فى نفس المستشفى من عملائها
were three times more likely to give birth
كانوا أكثر عرضةً لأن يلدوا
to a baby below a healthy weight.
أطفالاً تحت الوزن الصحي.
Jennie is making headway into what has been seen for decades
تضع (جيني) انطلاقة لما قد نُظِرَ له لعقود
as an almost intractable problem.
على أنه مشكلة عسيرة لدرجة كبيرة.
Some of you might be thinking,
ربما يفكر بعضكم،
all this one-on-one attention that The JJ Way requires
أن هذه العناية التى تتطلبها "طريقة جى جى"
must be too expensive to scale.
لابد أن تكلفتها عالية جداً.
Well, you'd be wrong.
حسناً، أنتم مخطؤون.
The visit with the provider is not the center of Jennie's model,
الزيارة للطبيب ليست هدف نموذج (جيني)،
and for good reason.
ولسبب وجيه.
Those visits are expensive, and in order to maintain her model,
تلك الزيارات باهظة الثمن وللحفاظ على نموذجها،
she's got to see a lot of clients to cover costs.
عليها أن تقابل الكثير من عملائها لتغطية التكاليف.
But Jennie doesn't have to spend a ton of time with each woman,
لكن لا يتوجب على (جيني) قضاء الكثير من الوقت مع كل إمرأة،
if all of the members of her team can provide the support, information
إذا ما تمكن كل أعضاء فريقها من تقديم الدعم والمعلومات
and care that her clients need.
والرعاية التى يحتاجها عملاؤها.
The beauty of Jennie's model is that she actually believes
يكمن جمال نموذج (جيني) في أنها تؤمن حقاً
it can be implemented in pretty much any health care setting.
بإمكانية تطبيقه تقريباً فى أى وضع للرعاية الصحية.
It's a revolution in care just waiting to happen.
إنه ثورة فى مجال الرعاية على وشك الحدوث.
These problems I've been sharing with you are big.
هذه المشاكل التى تشاركتها معكم كبيرة.
They come from long histories of racism, classism,
هي نتاج تاريخ طويل بسبب العنصرية والطبقية،
a society based on race and class stratification.
ومجتمع مبني على العرق والتقسيم الطبقي.
They involve elaborate physiological mechanisms
ينتهجون أليات فسيولوجية مفصّلة
meant to protect us,
بهدف حمايتنا،
that, when overstimulated, actually make us sick.
والتي تصيبنا بالمرض في حال استثارتها بشدة.
But if there's one thing I've learned from my work as a doula,
لكن إن كان هناك شئ واحد تعلمته من عملى كقابلة،
it's that a little bit of unconditional support can go a really long way.
أن القليل من الدعم غير المشروط يمكن أن يساعد كثيراً.
History has shown that people are incredibly resilient,
أثبت التاريخ أن الناس مرنين بصورة مذهلة،
and while we can't eradicate racism
وبينما لا نستطيع إستئصال العنصرية
or the stress that results from it overnight,
أو التوتر الناتج عنها بين ليلة وضحاها،
we might just be able to create environments that provide a buffer
فلربما نستطيع فقط خلق بيئات تخفف
to what people of color experience on a daily basis.
من ما يعانيه الناس الملونون يومياً.
And during pregnancy, that buffer can be an incredible tool
وأثناء الحمل يمكن أن يكون هذا التخفيف أداةً مذهلة
towards shifting the impact of racism
فى تغيير تأثير العنصرية
for generations to come.
للأجيال القادمة.
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)